<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: other | Aatos Jalo]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.aatosjalo.com/blog/categories/other/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.aatosjalo.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-02T12:32:28+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.aatosjalo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aatos Jalo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adding Finnish alphabets to US keyboard layout]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aatosjalo.com/blog/2015/01/25/adding-finnish-alphabets-to-us-keyboard-layout/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-25T12:04:47+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aatosjalo.com/blog/2015/01/25/adding-finnish-alphabets-to-us-keyboard-layout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t like Finnish keyboard layout that much. Way too many characters require
three keys to be pressed simultaneously. This is especially annoying when
programming, since to get, e.g., different types of brackets, you have to change
between Alt Gr and Shift quite heavily. Furthermore, Finnish layout has keys
like &lsquo;¤&rsquo;, which I have never used (and just recently learned that is used to
denote an unspecified currency). Many common characters used in programming are
dead keys, which makes them difficult to use. I haven&rsquo;t ever used the dead key
functionality in &lsquo;`&rsquo;, &lsquo;~&rsquo; or &lsquo;^&rsquo; and usually I try to use layout where that is
disabled. In Linux, there is usually a variant of Finnish layout without dead
keys, but not in Windows. To tackle these problems, I decided to try US layout.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I mostly write English, but sometimes I need Finnish and quite many words have
&lsquo;ä&rsquo; or &lsquo;ö&rsquo;. I don&rsquo;t like switching between different layouts, because I often
forget to change it back. One nice thing in a Finnish keyboard is that it has 105
keys, one more than the standard US keyboard. This extra key is located between
left shift and &lsquo;z&rsquo; and is bound to &lsquo;&lt;&rsquo; by default. In
<a href="http://arkku.com/dvorak/">ArkkuDvorak</a>, this key is used for &lsquo;ä&rsquo; and &lsquo;ö&rsquo;, so I
decided to create US layout with that addition. I don&rsquo;t remember when I have
needed those capitalized and I could manage those rare occasions with <code>M-c</code>.</p>

<p>Modifying keyboard layout in Windows requires <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/goglobal/bb964665.aspx">Microsoft Keyboard Layout Creator</a>
which is quite straightforward to use. There you can load the US layout and
change the extra key to whatever you want. You can find the source file for MKLC
<a href="http://aatosjalo.com/downloads/us-ae.klc">here</a> or even the ready-made installer <a href="http://aatosjalo.com/downloads/us-ae-oe.zip">here</a>.</p>

<p>In Linux this is even easier. With <code>xmodmap</code> you can modify your current X
keyboard bindings. By doing <code>xmodmap -pke &gt; ~/.Xmodmap</code>, you can dump your
current layout to a file. Then just by applying the following patch you can get
&lsquo;ä&rsquo; (adiaeresis) and &lsquo;ö&rsquo; (odiaeresis) to that extra key.</p>

<pre><code class="diff">--- .Xmodmap_default_us 2015-01-25 12:47:18.212591435 +0200
+++ .Xmodmap    2015-01-18 21:34:26.435894329 +0200
@@ -84,7 +88,7 @@
 keycode  91 = KP_Delete KP_Decimal KP_Delete KP_Decimal
 keycode  92 = ISO_Level3_Shift NoSymbol ISO_Level3_Shift
 keycode  93 =
-keycode  94 = less greater less greater bar brokenbar bar
+keycode  94 = adiaeresis odiaeresis less greater bar brokenbar bar
 keycode  95 = F11 F11 F11 F11 F11 F11 XF86Switch_VT_11
 keycode  96 = F12 F12 F12 F12 F12 F12 XF86Switch_VT_12
 keycode  97 =
</code></pre>

<p>Xmodmap can be read by <code>xmodmap ~/.Xmodmap</code> (be careful though, you might want
to test that it actually works by using some other filename). This is usually
read automatically when X starts, but you can also add this to
e.g. <code>.xinitrc</code>. While you are at it, you might want to make your <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?RemapCapsLock">caps lock act as a control</a>
by modifying the same file. For doing that on Windows, I have used
<a href="http://sharpkeys.codeplex.com/">this</a> application.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aatosjalo.com/blog/2014/06/12/hello/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-12T23:32:04+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aatosjalo.com/blog/2014/06/12/hello</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first post. I&rsquo;ll be writing about programming and somehow
related areas that I&rsquo;m interested in and want to learn more. Basically
I&rsquo;ll document what I have done and learned, mostly for myself, but if
someone manages to get here by googling, it&rsquo;s even better. At least
for the summer I should have some time to spend on this, but after
that the amount of posts will decrease.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>For the first real post I will write about Boyer-Moore string
searching algorithm. When I implemented it, I couldn&rsquo;t find any decent
explanation about the implementation of the good suffix rule. The
basics behind BM are quite easy to understand but the implementation
itself is not so straightforward. By writing about it, I&rsquo;ll see if I
really understood it.</p>

<p>Next, I would like to experiment a little with <a href="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/">Linux from scratch</a>. I have used many different
Linux distributions, but I don&rsquo;t have a clue what is required for a
working system after you have the kernel image. I have been using
Emacs for awhile, and it would be nice to try to setup Linux with as
few libraries and applications as possible and just use Emacs for
everything (as a terminal, shell etc.). I think it wouldn&rsquo;t be very
usable for the long run since it would miss a lot of modern features
but something like writing and uploading blog post on it should be
possible.</p>

<p>I chose <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> for my blogging needs since
it seems to be quite lightweight and just what I need (and of course,
who doesn&rsquo;t like Markdown?). It doesn&rsquo;t require anything on the server
side (except SSH access for easier deployment) and writing new posts
seems to be easy. I don&rsquo;t really know anything about blogging
platforms at this point and at first I thought that I have to use
Wordpress or Joomla which might have been little too heavyweight. As a
web hosting provider I chose <a href="https://www.webhotelli.fi/">Webhotelli.fi</a>
because it was quite cheap and offered SSH with their smallest plan
where providers only include SSH with more expensive plans (i.e. buy
more disk space to get SSH).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
